<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc5988 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5988.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc3987 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3987.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc3986 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'>
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?> 
<?rfc strict="yes"?> 
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?> 
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?> 
<?rfc compact="yes"?> 
<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200811" docName="draft-snell-more-link-relations-05"> 
  <front> 
    <title abbrev="More Link Relations"> 
      Additional Link Relation Registrations
    </title> 
 
    <author initials="J.M." surname="Snell" fullname="James M Snell"> 
      <address> 
        <email>jasnell@gmail.com</email> 
      </address> 
    </author> 
    
    <date month="August" year="2014" /> 
 
    <area>Applications</area> 
    <keyword>I-D</keyword> 
    <keyword>http</keyword> 
    <keyword>link</keyword> 
    <keyword>rel</keyword>
 
    <abstract> 
      <t>
        This specification registers a handful of new RFC 5988 
        Link Relation types.
      </t> 
    </abstract> 
 
  </front> 
  
  <middle> 
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction"> 
 
      <t>
        This specification defines and adds the following additional 
        link relation types to the IANA Registry of Link Relations
        established by <xref target="RFC5988"/>: to, bto, cc, bcc, 
        from, bfrom, source, scope, generator, provider, location, alias 
        and mentioned-by.
      </t>
      
      <t>
        Note that this document is a work-in-progress draft specification
        that does not yet represent a "standard". It is the intention of 
        this specification to propose a few new ideas and openly solicit 
        feedback on their definition and use. While this document might 
        eventually evolve into an RFC the ideas described herein have not 
        yet been broadly implemented and have definitions that may evolve
        through successive iterations of this draft.
      </t>
      
    </section> 
                              
    <section title="IANA Considerations"> 
      
      <t>
        The following Link Relations are added to the IANA Registry of 
        Link Relations:
      </t>
      
      <texttable>
        <ttcol>Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Description</ttcol>
        
        <c>id</c>
        <c>
          Specifies an IRI <xref target="RFC3987"/> or URI <xref target="RFC3986"/>considered 
          to represent the identity of the link context.
        </c>
        
        <c>to</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource that is considered to be part of the
          public primary audience of the link's context.
        </c>
        
        <c>bto</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource that is considered to be part of the
          private primary audience of the link's context.
        </c>
        
        <c>cc</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource that is considered to be part of the 
          public secondary audience of the link's context.
        </c>
        
        <c>bcc</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource that is considered to be part of the 
          private secondary audience of the link's context.
        </c>
        
        <c>from</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource that is publicly considered to be the originator
          of the link's context.
        </c>
        
        <c>bfrom</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource that is privately considered to be the orignator
          of the link's context.
        </c>
        
        <c>scope</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource that identifies the total population of entities
          for which the context is considered relevant. 
        </c>
        
        <c>source</c>
        <c>
          Refers to the original source of information contained by the 
          context resource.
        </c>
        
        <c>provider</c>
        <c>
          Refers to the resource that provided the context resource. 
          Typically, this would be used to identify the entity publishing
          the resource. 
        </c>
        
        <c>generator</c>
        <c>
          Refers to the resource that generated the context resource.
          Typically, this would be used to identify the software application
          that created the context resource.
        </c>
        
        <c>mentioned-by</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource that mentions the context resource in some 
          fashion. This, for example, would be used when an article mentions
          another article, or a social status update mentions a particular
          user, etc.
        </c>

        <c>mentions</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource mentioned by the context resource in some
          fashion. This, for example, would be used when an article mentions
          another article, or a social status update mentions a particular
          user, etc.
        </c>

        <c>derived-from</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource from which the context resource was derived.
        </c>

        <c>location</c>
        <c>
          References an IRI or URI representing a physical or logical location
          with which the context resource is associated.
        </c>

        <c>card</c>
        <c>
          References an IRI or URI representing a "card" summarizing
          the context resource. For instance, this may link to a VCard or 
          HTML document that provides summary information about and contact 
          information for a person, organization or community.
        </c>
        
      </texttable>
                  
    </section> 
 
    <section title="Security Considerations"> 
    
      <t>There are no additional security concerns introduced by this
      document.</t>
    
    </section> 
  </middle> 
 
  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc5988;
      &rfc3986;
      &rfc3987;
    </references>    
  </back>
  
</rfc> 
 